<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: zeroconf | Geekheads]]></title>
  <link href="http://www.geekheads.net/blog/categories/zeroconf/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://www.geekheads.net/"/>
  <updated>2013-10-18T23:18:18-05:00</updated>
  <id>http://www.geekheads.net/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Jack Lund]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Zeroconf Rocks!]]></title>
    <link href="http://www.geekheads.net/blog/2013/06/27/Zeroconf-Rocks/"/>
    <updated>2013-06-27T22:27:00-05:00</updated>
    <id>http://www.geekheads.net/blog/2013/06/27/Zeroconf-Rocks</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>I have a lot of computers on my network now &ndash; my laptop and desktop, my wife&rsquo;s 3(!) computers, her iPad, two Linux servers and miscellaneous other devices, along with my Raspberry Pi and two BeagleBone Blacks, so managing all these was starting to be a pain. So, just on a hunch, I wanted to see if <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Zero-configuration_networking">Bonjour/Zeroconf/Avahi</a> could help. I did some investigation, and it turns out that you can access any machines that advertise on Zeroconf by <em>name</em>.local. Since I work predominantly on Macs, I was already pretty comfortable with the idea of dynamically finding service. When I brought up my Bonjour Browser application, however, I was surprised: My two BeagleBone Blacks were already advertising (the wrong IP address for my network, but still)!</p>

<p>So, first step: set up the Raspberry Pi to do the same. Fortunately, the Internet came to the rescue, in the form of <a href="http://elinux.org/RPi_Advanced_Setup">this page</a> about setting up Zeroconf on the Pi. I just followed the instructions, and it worked.</p>

<p>Next, I had to fix my BeagleBone Blacks. To do this, I found the DHCP daemon config file, <code>/etc/udhcpd.conf</code>, which looked like this:</p>

<pre><code>start      192.168.7.1
end        192.168.7.1
interface  usb0
max_leases 1
option subnet 255.255.255.252
</code></pre>

<p>and which I changed to match my network:</p>

<pre><code>start      192.168.1.2
end        192.168.1.99
interface  usb0
max_leases 1
option subnet 255.255.255.0
</code></pre>

<p>Then, I just restarted them, and they suddenly had the right IP addresses.</p>

<p>Now, all I have to do to SSH into my Pi is do <code>ssh raspberry-pi.local</code>. For my BeagleBones, it would be <code>ssh beaglebone-red.local</code> or <code>ssh beaglebone-blue.local</code>.</p>

<p>W00t!!!!</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
