<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: jdk7 | Geekheads]]></title>
  <link href="http://www.geekheads.net/blog/categories/jdk7/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://www.geekheads.net/"/>
  <updated>2013-09-19T09:18:05-05:00</updated>
  <id>http://www.geekheads.net/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Jack Lund]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[VerifyError with JDK 7]]></title>
    <link href="http://www.geekheads.net/blog/2013/05/06/VerifyError-with-JDK-7/"/>
    <updated>2013-05-06T21:43:00-05:00</updated>
    <id>http://www.geekheads.net/blog/2013/05/06/VerifyError-with-JDK-7</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>We had been using nothing higher than JDK 6 with our project up until now, but when I built a new build machine using Fedora 18, JDK 7 was our only real option (okay, that and JDK 5). However, once I got things building using ant, I got the following cryptic error in the unit tests:</p>

<pre><code>java.lang.VerifyError: Expecting a stackmap frame at branch target 41 in method com.m2mci.correlation.CorrelationId.equals(Ljava/lang/Object;)Z at offset 24
</code></pre>

<p>After some <a href="http://www.javacraft.org/2012/07/cobertura-with-jdk7.html">digging</a>, I found out that the kind folks at Oracle/Sun had changed the bytecode in JDK 7 such that there was a verifier frame now included where there wasn&rsquo;t before. This is fine as long as everything knows about this, but we&rsquo;ve been using <a href="http://cobertura.sourceforge.net/">Cobertura</a> for code coverage, which instruments the bytecode, and which apparently doesn&rsquo;t know about the fancy new verifier stack frame. What&rsquo;s worse, they don&rsquo;t seem (from what I can tell from their website) to have any interest in adding it any time soon.</p>

<p>So, what to do? Our two alternatives are a) drop Cobertura, or b) include the JVM argument <code>-XX:-UseSplitVerifier</code> every time we run our code. To me, the former seems the better way to go, especially since we&rsquo;re not really <em>using</em> code coverage right now (we probably should, but for now, we&rsquo;re not).</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
