<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: java | Geekheads]]></title>
  <link href="http://jacklund.github.io/blog/categories/java/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://jacklund.github.io/"/>
  <updated>2014-04-13T11:22:50-05:00</updated>
  <id>http://jacklund.github.io/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Jack Lund]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Dependency Injection and the YAGNI principle]]></title>
    <link href="http://jacklund.github.io/blog/2014/04/13/dependency-injection-and-the-yagni-principle/"/>
    <updated>2014-04-13T10:07:00-05:00</updated>
    <id>http://jacklund.github.io/blog/2014/04/13/dependency-injection-and-the-yagni-principle</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>One of my new personal projects involves writing an application using <a href="http://nodejs.org">Node.js</a> and <a href="http://www.mongodb.org">MongoDB</a>. It&rsquo;s going to have a <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Representational_state_transfer">RESTful</a> interface for the services, and MongoDB as the database (I haven&rsquo;t decided about what I&rsquo;m going to use for the front-end, but <a href="http://angularjs.org">Angular.js</a> is a strong contender). I had looked at using <a href="http://www.mean.io/">mean.io</a> to build it, but after playing with it for a while, it seemed to bring in too many things I wouldn&rsquo;t end up needing, so I decided to build it all from scratch using <a href="https://github.com/mcavage/node-restify">Restify</a> for the RESTful services.</p>

<p>I&rsquo;m writing it in an <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Model%E2%80%93view%E2%80%93controller">MVC</a>-ish way (really, since it&rsquo;s REST, it&rsquo;s more like MRC &ndash; Model &ndash; Route &ndash; Controller) where the top-level module requires routing modules from whatever Javascript files are in a particular directory (<code>lib/routes</code>), and calls them as functions, passing in the Restify server instance so the routes can be set up. Each route would call a corresponding &ldquo;controller&rdquo;, which would bring in a corresponding &ldquo;model&rdquo;, and set up the functions that each route would use to do its thing. So, the question became: how do I pass the database connection down to the model?</p>

<p>When I looked at how mean.io does things, I noticed that they use a dependency injection package called &ldquo;<a href="https://github.com/idottv/dependable">dependable</a>&rdquo;. The way it works is that you create a &ldquo;container&rdquo; using dependable, and register dependencies in it, then the module that needs it would grab the container and read the dependencies out of it.</p>

<p>First of all, this <em>isn&rsquo;t</em> dependency injection, because the module needing the dependencies has to actively retrieve the dependencies from a container, rather than having them <em>injected</em> (hence the term &ldquo;dependency <em>injection</em>&rdquo;). Of course, it doesn&rsquo;t really matter what you call it, the package performs the basic function well &ndash; removing the coupling between the module creating the dependency and the module using it. However, I question whether it makes sense for the mean.io stack to use it in this case, for the simple reason that I believe this is a case where coupling is fine, in that the top-level module is already coupled to the routing modules, which are coupled to the controllers, which are coupled to the models, so pretending that they don&rsquo;t know anything about one another is kind of silly.</p>

<p>This speaks to another issue I&rsquo;ve seen a lot of (especially in the Java world), which is a lack of understanding of the role <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/You_aren't_gonna_need_it">YAGNI</a> (&ldquo;You Ain&rsquo;t Gonna Need It&rdquo;) should play in programming.</p>

<p>One of the most egregious examples of this (which I&rsquo;ve been guilty of myself) is the idea, in Java, that any class which is a dependency of another class should have an interface which the depending class uses as a proxy for it. In other words, if I have a class <code>A</code> which contains class <code>B</code>, I feel like I have to create a <code>BInterface</code> interface which <code>A</code> really contains, but which is implemented using <code>B</code>. The idea behind this is: what if, some day, I create a new class <code>C</code> which implements <code>BInterface</code>, but with a different implementation. Then, I don&rsquo;t have to change <code>A</code>&rsquo;s declaration, I just change where it creates <code>B</code> to create <code>C</code>.</p>

<p>This is fundamentally the same idea as the one where you have to dependency inject everything &ndash; you want everything to be perfectly flexible, so you don&rsquo;t have to make changes when the implementation changes. However, the hidden expense here is that you now have twice as many classes/modules that you have to manage. Admittedly, half of them are interfaces, so they don&rsquo;t do much, but it&rsquo;s still adding a lot of complexity where it isn&rsquo;t needed, because, chances are, YAGNI. And, in those places where you do need it, creating a new interface is trivial (especially in something like Eclipse), so you can do it then.</p>

<p>Flexibility <em>always</em> comes with a cost. The key to a good design is knowing where to add flexibility, and where not to. In the case of my Node.js code, I decided to pass the database connection through the route, simply because I think it&rsquo;s fine that the top-level module understands that the routes might need to pass it down to their dependencies &ndash; that&rsquo;s what having it as a parameter <em>means</em> &ndash; either &ldquo;I&rsquo;m going to need it&rdquo;, or &ldquo;one of my children will need it&rdquo;. Either way, it doesn&rsquo;t make the design any less clean, and, if something changes where I <em>do</em> need dependency injection, well, I can always add it later. YAGNI.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Creating RESTEasy Project with Eclipse and Maven]]></title>
    <link href="http://jacklund.github.io/blog/2013/05/20/Creating-RESTEasy-Project-with-Eclipse-and-Maven/"/>
    <updated>2013-05-20T00:00:00-05:00</updated>
    <id>http://jacklund.github.io/blog/2013/05/20/Creating-RESTEasy-Project-with-Eclipse-and-Maven</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Handy safety tip: to create a RESTEasy-friendly Maven project in Eclipse, do the following:</p>

<ol>
<li>Create the project as a simple Maven project</li>
<li>In the project Properties &ndash;> Project Facets, make the project faceted, and select &ldquo;Dynamic Web Module&rdquo; (you may get a NullPointerException, but it doesn&rsquo;t seem to matter). Under &ldquo;Further Configuration&hellip;&rdquo;, point the WebApp directory to be <code>src/main/webapp</code>, and have it create the <code>web.xml</code> file.</li>
<li>Under &ldquo;Web Content Settings&rdquo;, set the Context root</li>
<li>Under &ldquo;Deployment Assembly&rdquo;, select &ldquo;Add&hellip;&rdquo;, select &ldquo;Java Build Path Entries&rdquo;, and select &ldquo;Maven Dependencies&rdquo;. It should put them in <code>WEB-INF/lib</code>.</li>
<li>Add the code and the dependencies to the <code>pom.xml</code>. Make sure to add the RESTEasy stuff to the <code>web.xml</code> file.</li>
</ol>


<p>You should be able to deploy it from Eclipse into Tomcat without any issues</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[VerifyError with JDK 7]]></title>
    <link href="http://jacklund.github.io/blog/2013/05/06/VerifyError-with-JDK-7/"/>
    <updated>2013-05-06T21:43:00-05:00</updated>
    <id>http://jacklund.github.io/blog/2013/05/06/VerifyError-with-JDK-7</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>We had been using nothing higher than JDK 6 with our project up until now, but when I built a new build machine using Fedora 18, JDK 7 was our only real option (okay, that and JDK 5). However, once I got things building using ant, I got the following cryptic error in the unit tests:</p>

<pre><code>java.lang.VerifyError: Expecting a stackmap frame at branch target 41 in method com.m2mci.correlation.CorrelationId.equals(Ljava/lang/Object;)Z at offset 24
</code></pre>

<p>After some <a href="http://www.javacraft.org/2012/07/cobertura-with-jdk7.html">digging</a>, I found out that the kind folks at Oracle/Sun had changed the bytecode in JDK 7 such that there was a verifier frame now included where there wasn&rsquo;t before. This is fine as long as everything knows about this, but we&rsquo;ve been using <a href="http://cobertura.sourceforge.net/">Cobertura</a> for code coverage, which instruments the bytecode, and which apparently doesn&rsquo;t know about the fancy new verifier stack frame. What&rsquo;s worse, they don&rsquo;t seem (from what I can tell from their website) to have any interest in adding it any time soon.</p>

<p>So, what to do? Our two alternatives are a) drop Cobertura, or b) include the JVM argument <code>-XX:-UseSplitVerifier</code> every time we run our code. To me, the former seems the better way to go, especially since we&rsquo;re not really <em>using</em> code coverage right now (we probably should, but for now, we&rsquo;re not).</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
